American Artifact Collection ARC.0064
Library and Archives
American Artifact Collection
2009
ARC.0064
Library and Archives
4.07 Linear feet (1 folder, 1 shared flat file drawer)
The American Artifact Collection consists of 12 posters created by some of the artists portrayed in the film American Artifact: The Rise of American Rock Poster, and a press kit and promotional materials for the film. The film chronicles the history of the rock concert poster, from its origins in 1960s San Francisco to its re-emergence in the 21st century. American Artifact was released in 2009 and directed by Merle Becker. Seen in a broader context, the collection provides insights to fringe and underground artists of the past fifty years, and how art is influenced by music, culture, and society, and how music, culture, and society, in return, influence art. The American Artifact Collection is arranged first by format; the posters are arranged alphabetically by artist.
Becker, Merle
Bell, Leia
Emek, 1970-
Hampton, Justin
Hatch Show Print (Firm)
Imagine, Paul
Loren, Dennis
Mouse, Stanley, 1940-
Rogers, Jermaine
Shaw, Chris
Sperry, Chuck
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Patrons must sign the Acknowledgment of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights statement on the Researcher Registration form before using this collection. Consult the Library and Archives in advance of your visit to ensure access to these materials is available.
Administrative History
For the film American Artifact, director Merle Becker crossed the country interviewing rock poster artists from different eras to discover that America is currently in the midst of a 21st century "rock poster art movement," where thousands of artists around the country are doing silk screened rock poster art inspired by their local scene, the music of the time, and the spirit of an era.
This film, which includes interviews with over 30 artists, takes the viewer through the different decades and incarnations of this art form, and spends time with, arguably, some of the finest artists of this genre, talking about what inspired their truly American works of art.
The film features: Mark Arminski, Julie Belcher, Leia Bell, Kevin Bradley, Art Chantry, COOP, Mat Daly, Ron Donovan, EMEK, Gary Grimshaw, Justin Hampton, Derek Hess, Paul Imagine, Frank Kozik, Lindsey Kuhn, Dennis Loren, Mike Martin, Tara McPherson, Stanley Mouse, Victor Moscoso, Jim Pollock, Print Mafia, Jermaine Rogers, Jay Ryan, Scrojo, Chris Shaw, Jim Sherraden & Hatch Show Print, David Singer, Chuck Sperry, Winston Smith, Stainboy, Randy Tuten, Steve Walters, and Jeff Wood.
Producer/director Merle Becker is a 17+ year veteran of film and television. Credits include CBS Tony Awards, Beavis & Butt-Head, Comedy Central's Tough Crowd With Colin Quinn, and MTV's Total Request Live. She has also worked on several feature films, including Rising Low (with Warren Haynes and Phil Lesh).
Custodial History
The American Artifact Collection was received by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, Inc. as a gift from Merle Becker of Freakfilms, Inc. on January 12, 2010.
Separated Materials
Two copies of American Artifact: The Rise of American Rock Poster, the deluxe double DVD, have been transferred to the library collection. Please search for the "American Artifact Collection" in the library catalog for a list of donated titles. If you are unable to find what you are looking for, consult the Library and Archives staff to ensure these materials are available.
Becker, Merle; Kelley, Alton, 1940-2008; American artifact (Motion picture: 2009); Film posters; Graphic artists; Posters; Rock music--Posters
- Bell, Leia, 2009; 17" x 12" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 1)
  Limited Print Run
  144/155
- Hatch Show Print, 2009; 24" x13.5" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 2)
  Non-numbered edition of 150
- Imagine, Paul, 2009; 11" x 17" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 3)
  171/215
- Loren, Dennis, 2009; 19" x 13" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 4-6)
- Mouse, Stanley, 2009; 19" x 13" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 7-8)
  General note
  This item includes a black-and-white photograph of Stanley Mouse and Alton Kelley.
- PNE (Emek, Jermaine Rogers, Justin Hampton), 2009; 24" x 27" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 9)
  Non-numbered edition of 35
- Scrojo, 2009; 21.5" x 11" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 10)
  122/150
- Shaw, Chris, 2009; 29" x 20 (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 11)
- Sperry, Chuck, 2009; 29.5" x 20.25" (Drawer-folder FF.1.2-2, Object 12)
- Press kit and promotional cards, 2009 (Folder 11)